hi welcome back i just got some good
news
that they just experienced a small
earthquake in taiwan congratulations
i'm sure that's some bodhisattva uh
in our group congratulations uh
so yeah the story about the 500 ducks
or geese i guess comes from i
found it it's in the sutra of the wise
and the foolish
and if you'd like to read it someday we
can
we're kind of behind in this class so we
gotta start
speeding up okay
and the next picture that i wanted to
show
we're going to talk about infinity okay
we're going to talk about
what does it feel like to jump
on to jump from
one planet to another without number
okay without any number billions and
billions of planets okay well i say
billions because it's an easy word to
say
but there's no number okay and you and
you jump on that
you leap across that many planets to to
make connection with that many people
okay and there's a connection
between the hearing
about it many times and then
experiencing it
infinite times okay and he's going to
talk about that all right here we go
this is talking about a king called
ajatashatru
ajata means not born yet adjeta
and ja came into genetics for example
and satru means enemy as
arti uh so ajata shattra means
before he was before he came out of his
mother's womb
a a what do you call it future seer
a seer said that he would kill his
father
okay and so he was called the unborn
enemy
a judge to shut through but later in
fact he did
but later he uh repented and became a
famous saint and uh
so he had a very by the time he became
king
he had a very heavy seed for emptiness
okay
uh duke cup and he
had prepared a meal for the
for the monks in his kingdom
uh majutri attended as a bodhisattva
and the king tried to offer him a
golden robe made of pure gold
threads of pure gold and then
suddenly manjushri disappeared
okay and he's standing there with the
room
to give it to magician my juicer just
disappeared
so then he's like wow what am i supposed
to do about that
and he tried it he said let me try it on
myself maybe it'll fit me
and he and he put it on and suddenly he
disappeared
after he put the robe on the golden robe
on and
then uh
because he had a heavy seat in his mind
because he had attended teachings about
emptiness before
when he saw these different kinds of
physical
disappearances it triggered
the perception emptiness in his mind so
this is
the kind of story that's very dangerous
because people will go around you know
trying to get someone to disappear so
they can see emptiness you
so these are the kind of dangerous
stories
uh it it doesn't mean that
if someone disappears when you're trying
to give them a gift
that you're about to see emptiness it
doesn't mean that
but it is true that there can be
small personal experiences of absence
which remind you of emptiness what's the
most famous one in the dci
system small absence of an expected
object
that's a good one i'm thinking of
something else
in the kitchen something in your pocket
okay yeah you're looking for your credit
card and you take
it's always jb i don't know why he's
always the person who
who who has to pay for me but
uh i i take my i change my pants before
i go out to dinner with jb
and then i forget the credit card and
then i'm looking in my pocket for the
credit card
and it's true that the absence of an
expected object in your pocket
can remind you of emptiness uh
but that doesn't mean you should try to
take jb out as often as possible
and forget your credit card okay so okay
so try to
distinguish okay what they're saying is
[Music]
keep coming to classes keep learning
keep listening everything you hear has
an
effect on your mind every everything you
ever experience
will come up later in your life uh
that's a different experience okay if
you can
plant some seeds for emptiness
you know by attending alarm room
teaching in 2021
then in 2030 uh
you might be at a restaurant with jb
still trying to get us dinner
and um and you'll reach into your pocket
and you'll have an experience of
emptiness because
because of the seed you planted 10 years
before okay
so try to expose yourself to teachings
all right and i i like to call it the
four spaces meditation here's a picture
of it
[Music]
sitting on your back in the
in a in a nice grassy field or a nice
rocky uh
plateau at that moment uh and watching
the sky which is what this little girl
is doing
uh it's not emptiness but if you have
seeds
because you went to the alarm room
teachings and you were too busy to
really focus on it
but you heard the teachings those seeds
will affect you later
as they did the 500
ducks or geese okay all right good
all right which takes us to
today's class we're hopelessly behind
all right um
we're still on this theme that he's
going back to the theme
then if you're a bodhisattva
you can help other people just by
being someone they can offer coffee to
or something like that
okay so
and he gives the example of this deva so
deva means
if you if you meditate a lot in this
life
and you because you're meditating a lot
you don't have time to hurt people as we
usually do
and then uh because of that good karma
default good karma you uh
become born like superman or iron man or
wonder woman
1984 okay
you become this beautiful handsome
strong deva okay if you
succeed in reaching bodhichitta
you attract these powerful beings
i i like to say these are people who
use planets as marbles to play games
you know they are so powerful they can
they can flip a planet with their finger
okay this these are dema uh
so though he mentions brahma
and shakra he mentions a few of them
and he says they will be attracted to
you
and they will make offerings to you and
their influence is that you will have
enjoy good health
awesome okay and they will drop che
what's dropbo
in tibetan topo friend yeah they will be
your friend
they will hang out with you maybe you
don't even see them
but they make your life easier okay they
are like
kelsey being your attendant invisibly
all the time and they're just doing
things for you you don't even know
that's one of the effects of being a
body sufferer
joe please
symbolic this is now starting a very
very very famous
topic about where do buddhas come from
okay and this is going to take us i
don't know
maybe a couple days i don't know but
it's very famous
extremely famous so the question is
where do buddhas come from
jope sangei total buddhist
samyaksambula right chandusembale
they come from bodhisattvas okay where
do you
how do you get a buddha well you need to
god you need to get a bodhisattva
then that that's where you get a buddha
what's the raw material for a buddha
it's a bodhisattva where hey if you want
a new buddha how do you get one
we gotta start with a buddy supper okay
well how do you get a new body supper
well you gotta get a new body cheetah
that's where they come from
okay where did buddhists come from if i
want a
new buddha whether how'd i get one well
go find a body stop and
they they're about to be a buddha well
if i want to find a new bodhisattva what
do i do we'll go find someone who just
got bunny china
look for buddy china that makes
bodhisattvas buddhists make buddhas
therefore and this is a very very famous
idea in buddhism buddhas respect
bodhisattvas
more than other buddhas
buddhas respect bodhisattvas more than
they do other buddha
okay well yes pals like why
well i'm about to he's about to give you
like 10 pages about it
uh and and let's talk about it okay
why is it that a buddha would rather
meet a bodhisattva
than another buddha okay that's a good
question right
all right here we go and i have a
picture for you guys
and maybe maybe uh wrong guy
this is a different guy there you go uh
i don't know about you but i i had a
good time in school and i had wonderful
teachers
and after i left school and went to
college and started my life
i used to go back to the school and meet
my teachers in fact i just met
my sixth grade teacher that's 50 years
ago
and we still like we're still close
friends and
it's a it's a nice thing to to go back
and see your roots
where did you come from right go back
and meet the people who made you who you
are
uh and so that's
part of the answer paul it's the
pleasure
of going back to the sixth grade teacher
who made you the negative translator you
are now
50 years ago and they did you know
so it's like honoring where you came
from
okay honoring the person your parents or
your teachers or
okay so get in the mood when buddhists
want to have a good time
they try to connect with who they used
to be
where they came from their roots okay so
it's all about roots
after all doesn't the sutra say
doesn't lord buddha say in the sutra
i ask you to bow down to the
crescent moon and not the full moon
i ask you to bow down to the crescent
moon
we have a crescent moon going on right
now and not the full moon
okay what does it mean
yeah yeah nice bow down to the person
who has bodhichitta who's gonna become a
buddha
i would rather that you guys respect
bodhisattvas
even then buddhas because that's where
our roots are that's where we came from
okay it's an interesting concept and and
then lord buddha states it in the sutras
by saying
he just he states it in kind of a secret
way he says
i want you to bow down to crescent moons
not to full moons
okay and being a nerd
veronica says i'm a nerd i don't know
but uh i went and found that quotation
it's in the ratnakuta
which is called the it's a special
section of the buddhist teachings called
the
pile of jewels
and it's in a in a section
called the story of kashapa
okay
[Music]
so here we have a picture that that can
help you remember
okay and i i always like to think of the
muslim
sign of islam and you know it's easy to
imagine
that the crescent is more holy even than
the full moon
okay so so
that's a connection you can make every
time you see this symbol of islam
you can think about bodhisattvas all
right
okay they should do kandang a lot of
[Music]
there's also another quotation in sutra
where lord buddha says
if you love me bow down to bodhisattvas
and not to buddhas okay if you have
faith in me
i ask you please honor the bodhisattvas
even more than the buddhists those of
you who have faith in me
i ask you show it by bowing down to
where i came from
and not who i am it's beautiful
something beautiful and that comes from
the same
sutra you can find it in the same
situation
now yay i love him because he always
explains things he's like tonka or
choniloma
and he says hey maybe you guys are
wondering
why okay you know
hey why is that well chandra samba
shinto
listen and i i
suddenly last night i was reviewing this
for the class and i
it struck me um
my my mom had a station wagon because
she had four boys
you probably know about this though and
um
so this is like an old suv but big bag
in the back you could stuff like three
four kids in the backpack
and keep them out of trouble mostly and
uh
she would uh when i became a teenager
and i could drive and i had this
girlfriend named veronica
she would uh loan me the car and
that's a great car for dave okay
and then sometimes you would drive us
somewhere you know
and and it'd be like wow
you know your mom is driving two
teenagers around
and i mean frankly we were making out in
the back
i mean we didn't we didn't show her we
were making up
you know what i mean but
just get this picture in your mind of
the mom
who's supposed to be making sure the
kids don't make out
is driving them around in a station and
they're making out in the back okay i'm
just saying
why you got this picture geshe-la
chandra semba shindar shuknay
when bodhisattvas want to get in their
divine chariots
and enjoy the five objects of the senses
with each other
got it station wagon back backpack
uh shinta demba shenmena
if they can't find any horses to pull
the
chariot around the buddha will come
and offer himself as the bureau
okay got it when the buddhist officers
want to make out
in their chariots and there's no horses
available to pull them around the mom
which is lord buddha will come and pull
the chariot around
to honor the buddhist office are the
bodhisattvas doing something important
no they're making out in the back okay
do you
[Music]
they are having fun with their enjoyment
of the five objects of the census it
means they're making out okay
and and the buddha
will come and drag them around so they
can make out and
god it's maybe buddha
maybe lord buddha respects bodhisattvas
maybe
buddha has a soft spot in his heart
for bodhisattvas thanks he's trying to
prove it
by the way i found that uh i found that
one too
god bless all god bless all the gold
clubs
uh you know i i can just go
and ask the database and i will find the
sutra
sometimes i think pabunko machine would
be really jealous of us
you know it takes about one minute i
used to sit and
flip through scriptures for days
to find one thing now it's now it takes
about two minutes
you know so anyway guess where it is
it's in the sutra samuchaya which is a
it's a it's a collection of stories from
sutra assembled by
nagarjuna himself so by the way [__]
if you want to know who john brady was
in his past life
uh nagarjuna was fixated with saving
ancient books
that was his thing so who knows
so anyway uh he wrote a book called my
favorite quotations
from sutra and it's in there okay he
talks about that quotation
where the buddhas are dragging around
these chariots
where the buddhist officers are having
fun in the back
okay all right i knew that would come in
handy someday
uh papa taboo
shariputra who is the hero of the
heart sutra heart situated
he could stay in meditation for millions
of years if he wished to
okay de la deshan shepe means
but the buddha didn't pay him any
special
honor okay he he could sit
in meditation much longer
than any other disciple but the buddha
didn't think it was such a big deal
he wouldn't drag his chariot around
just because he could meditate for so
long okay
and sanjay ki as long as
[Music]
and then one day apparently and i
couldn't find this story
in the scriptures but uh the buddha had
extra food in his wisdom bowl
we don't call it a begging bowl
and and the buddha said it
put it on the table and then manjushi
was like
hey could i have some of that you know
can i
take uh what was that this morning tim
uh
sweet roll small pastry
like if geschlock went up to tim and
said don't show me another one i'll give
him uh no i'm just kidding it's okay
it's okay it's okay
uh
yeah and like if tim said oh look it's
like we got pastries and then he said
and then geshe-la said yeah i'll take
one and then
tim went and the pastries sink down into
the earth
you know some buddha asked manjushri hey
you want a pastry in my juice like yeah
especially one of yours you know and he
said
and they sank down into the ground why
because he was trying to say i don't
think he's
cool unless he's got bodhichitta okay
then i would offer him my pasty
so he he kind of dissed manjushri and i
guess he didn't have bodhichitta at that
point in in the story
okay uh or
or and i this is how i like to read this
story okay
because i don't i'm not aware of a story
where manjushru is not at least the
bodhisattva
i'm not aware of a time in the
scriptures that i've read
of course there was a time when he
wasn't the bunny stopper but i'm not
aware that
there's ever he's ever not a bodhisattva
in our scriptures today
and i think uh
lord buddha is trying to honor the
source
of life which is the earth okay i
i think lord buddha is trying to honor
he's offering
the leftover pastries in his bowl
to the dirt to the biochar
uh of earth because that's where
everything that's where all life comes
from
i think i think personally in this story
lord buddha commands his bowl to descend
into the
earth the soil because that's the source
of
all life in the same way that a
bodhisattva is the source of all
buddhists so he's
it's a story about roots it's a story
about where does all life come from
and so buddha offers his
food to mother earth and not to this
high bodhisattva
okay got it i think it's very beautiful
okay i couldn't find the story though
all right we finished the fourth benefit
which was what remember the picture is a
coffee in a coffee shop
it's probably peach tree cafe if it ever
opens
[Music]
well there's this sexy thing that if you
become a body sufferer
yeah then someone gives you a coffee
they're gonna go
they're gonna have bliss for a thousand
years isn't it fun to be the one
who's caused that okay
that think about how fun it is to buddy
but a bodhisattva
okay it just be so much fun
someone looks at you in a convenience
store and smiles
they get to go to heaven for 20 000
years
and to be the person who's the lookie
who gets looked at
and sends them to the preparedness for
twenty thousand years
wouldn't that be fun you're like hey
smile at me
you know and then they smile at you and
you're like aha i got you
[Music]
[Laughter]
i think it's really cool all right
next benefit number five by the way this
whole retreat
is about 10 cool things that are going
to happen to you
if you can become a buddy surfer here's
number five
it's much much say lapton
lopchen means big waves on the ocean
and it's the tibetan word for
massively effective
okay lup means uh ocean waves
like not a tidal wave not a tsunami but
just big normal waves
and it's the tibetan word for
extremely powerful potential
and i like the picture of
here we go this is uh
during the reign of queen guilty
as the director of diamond and uh
you know after 20 years
15 years we got we decided to build some
real roads and
we had a fantastic response from
people all over the world especially in
asia singapore
taiwan different friends
in different countries uh
finally after 20 years of hard work
uh we built some real roads here by the
way it's not finished and i'm not
finished asking for the money
uh but we can talk about it later uh
i also don't like to talk about money
all the time but you do need money to
build roads
so why are we talking about that gesla
when we first got here to diamond
mountain
and we decided to build some cabins
we realized we needed a road to get to
the place where we were going to build
the cabin
so we used to form a a line of people
like 20 people across
and we'd say okay everybody take one
step and we take one step
and we say pick up all the rocks in
front of you and then we'd all pick up
rocks and throw them on the side and
then
we say okay did everybody throw their
rocks yeah one more step
and then there'd be more rocks and we'd
throw those and
and we did that for like a cat remember
i think it was like
a month or something and we got like
100 meters it took a it took
over 20 people a month to clear the
rocks
in you know in 10 20 feet
you know it's not leptin
it's not what efficient it's not
effective
much better to have one you got that
picture much better to have these
machines right that machine uh the last
one yeah
that machine i went down to look at it
the wheel is taller than me
you know just the wheel on on the
machine is taller than me
i was like wow these things are cool
that's the fifth benefit of bodhichitta
okay you want to make good karma
you want a karma making machine
get body tenor okay much more efficient
okay it's like massive earth mover
not like picking up rocks and throwing
them okay although it was fun right
was it fun i know it was kind of hot
okay
the fifth benefit is reflected in a
quotation by a llama
called nukrumba champion
if you're just able to get
like a tiny experience of buddy china
and sometimes you do you know before you
become a bodhisattva you do get
these blessed moments of you know
a love for everybody it happens
like once every few years or something i
remember
being in a garden and it's an old
british garden
in the himalayan foothills it had been
overrun
by the forest and you just break into
this garden
and there's all these old british
orchids and beautiful flowers
growing wild inside a beautiful wall
and it was abandoned long ago but i just
had this
moment there of of some special moment
right so we do get special moments
that are similar to bodhichitta okay
if you just get a moment like that says
new grumba
three things happen number one
in that blessed i stayed in that garden
like 20 minutes or so i don't remember
but it it intense good karma intense
collections of good karma
while you're having this transformative
moment i hate that
expression okay secondly
uh
[Music]
the what do you call blinders on a horse
the covers on your eyes are torn off
briefly you have this moment of what do
you call it
it's like bliss but it's not bliss
anyway intense well-being
there's a word uh you have this
it's like a sacred moment it happens to
you right a few times
yeah ecstasy it happens for
10 minutes 20 minutes every couple years
it's close to buddy today right so
and during that time you can see clearly
you can see your life clearly
you can see what's important you can see
what's not important okay
that's the second benefit of even having
a
moment like that a moment of divine
connection which you can't predict it
you can't make it happen
but it happens every once in a while and
then thirdly parche qian qurang himself
um all the problems you've been having
in your life
up to that blessed moment
seem to drop away obstacles drop away so
three things
you collect intense good karma
you see more clearly and your problems
slough off for a while
okay he said just having this kind of
blessed divine moment where you feel
close to bodhichitta
has these three effects intense good
karma is collected
you see what's important
clearly and suddenly your problems
aren't so big anymore okay all right
um here's a picture
this is my version of a blessed moment
okay
it's like a huge car wash machine
you know and uh
it's it's gathering good karma cleaning
see removing obstacles to your vision
and then uh
removing problems past problems it's
like going through a huge spiritual car
wash how's that
okay you do have such moments
even before you have 100 complete
body tether right okay all right
[Music]
uh art art angle my my deep dear friend
who translated this book so well
and it took him 20 years uh
he he identifies new roomba as having
lived
about 800 years ago okay um
jane who's jay lama
said
this bodhichitta is like
alchemical elector okay
what is that so i don't know in ancient
times
people were always thinking there was
some kind of
juice that if you poured it on iron
it would become gold it's called the
alchemist
elixir right so
it's very popular in the ancient
tradition to refer to bodhichitta
as the alchemists elixir okay
why anybody want to guess for a hundred
dollars
why should bodhichitta be called
a special
elixir which turns iron into gold
because it turns the normal being into a
buddha nice
did i say hundred bucks the focus of a
virtue from one being
okay 50 bucks each yeah the point is
and he's going to make this point later
right now your body is flush
and no matter how much yoga you do i can
tell you
and no matter even if you eat well which
i haven't done that well but um
it's gonna fall apart okay and it's
you know do what you want eat as many
vitamins as you want it's still gonna
fall apart
okay so and that we said yesterday you
are
chained to this you know
defective from the factory
body and it will fall apart but
if you apply the elixir it will turn
into a
rainbow body okay so that's then the
steel the iron
will turn to gold okay your
human flesh will turn into a buddhist
rainbow body
okay uh
it's a gold mine of good karma a body
chill is a gold mine of good karma
um this quotation is from a
a book by some couple called larmium
duden
which is his tiny alarm rim so he wrote
a big alarm rim
he wrote a medium alarm rim he rode a
small alarm rim and then he wrote a tiny
alarm room
and the tiny lamrim is the sexiest one
okay because it's called
nyam gur okay say nyam guru
gur means uh a spiritual song
and yam means based on his own personal
life so it's not like tonkapa
to talk about himself he does not talk
about himself ever
very rarely but in this poem
he talks about his own spiritual life
and it's very beautiful
you know and the the line that i
like he he will describe
some beautiful thing that happened to
him in his spiritual life
and then he'll say the same sentence
ready
noun george saying
[Music]
he refers to himself as a high yogi uh
nanjora
right hey
that's the way i did it that's the way i
got to where i am
target keikyong if you guys are tanda
his name is thunder who seeks for
liberation
uh those of you who are trying to hey
you should do the same do what i did
it's very unusual for tonkata to say oh
i got to this level
and here's how i got there but in this
one
tiny poem not tiny a couple pages
in this one short long rim
he talks about his own experiences and
then he tells you how to do it
and it's very beautiful maybe we should
study that someday
that'd be amazing but it's a beautiful
beautiful
and then this refrain keeps coming
that's how i the great yogi reached
where i am
hey you guys are trying to okay it's
very beautiful
so that's where this quotation comes
from bodhichitta is like the alchemical
elixir
and you should you should get it too
like i did okay
all right the first time i read it i
thought it's so uh
unbuddhist especially for its own copper
he never talks about himself
but that that's a beautiful beautiful
word okay by the way
um milo repa wrote
gorboom the hundred thousand songs
uh which is not a hundred thousand but
it's a lot
okay all right uh here's an alchemist
i found a picture of an alchemist i
don't like the guy he looks a little
evil or something
but uh just imagine he's turning
steel iron into gold and
that's the idea so imagine this blue
liquid that looks like mouthwash is
actually bodhichitta and it's gonna turn
your mortal body
into a enlightened being's body
okay and and what's in the bottle
[Music]
but what is it really body tuner yay
okay
all right um
we have about five minutes oh yeah we
finished one class today
uh okay i call the next class which is
actually technically class four
a tim i promise we'll catch up somehow i
always do say that right
i i call this uh fourth class a
delightful way to pile up good karma
so that's the subject delightful ways to
get
piles of good karma okay so let's start
at least
and now we go to shantideva master
shanti deva's
guide to the police office way of life
because pablanco
bache is feeling happy
about the alchemy example
okay he wants to hit st he wants to hang
with that example ready
sergey in number what's the
highest alchemy elixir in the universe
it transforms this
filthy rotten corpse
of a human body into rin chen
rin tang mein okay it's a it's a planet
in tibetan uh rinchen
means jewel rin tang means
value so he's making a pun on rin
like rinpoche okay rinpoche means
valuable okay yeah so he says
you can take this body
this rotting corpse and turn it into
a precious gem
something like that it doesn't come
through in english so well
precious precious city something like
that
anyway you can turn it into jewel okay
all right chanti samshay
therefore please work hard on your
bodhichitta okay
who said that shanti duma that's master
the master shanti devas
guide to the police office way of life
the
whole first section the whole first five
pages or so
is this advertisement in shanti devas
words
okay so so pabong kumche is stealing
everything from shanti
you know the first five pages of that
famous bodhisattvas
manual is a
is a sales job and it's it's
perfectly matches what pabonko rimsey
wants to say so he's using it the pieces
from it okay
all right next picture we still have
three minutes let's use them
oh i'm sorry no that's been we're gonna
stop there